Register of the Monique Garnier-Lançon Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Monique Garnier-Lançon papers,
1963-1996
97003
Hoover Institution Archives
52 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (26.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, conference papers, agenda, memoranda, studies, press releases, clippings, serial issues, other printed matter, and audiovisual material, relating to French foreign and cultural relations, European defense policy and collective security, and international anti-communist movements.
Number of Containers: 63 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box
Garnier-Lançon, Monique, 1928-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1928 July 12 Born, Privas, France
1944-1946 Studies in history, Faculté de lettres, Lyons
1962-1971 Journalist and producer, O.R.T.F. (Organisation de la Radio-Télévision Française)
1977-1989 Adjointe au maire, mayor's office, Paris
1983-1989 Vice-president, European Institute for Security
Awards and honors Chevalier de la Légion d'honneur et des Palmes académiques
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1997, the Monique Garnier-Lançon papers in the Hoover Institution Archives document the career of a figure active in both the French political establishment and in international defense policy circles. The bulk of the papers are concerned with Garnier-Lançon's close involvement in the 1980s with the European Institute for Security Matters (EIS), an organization under whose auspices largely conservative opinion makers debated defense policy issues and lobbied for increased military spending by West European countries in the last years of the Cold War.
The EUROPEAN INSTITUTE FOR SECURITY MATTERS (EIS) FILE contains materials that detail European attitudes, especially in the defense establishment, toward security issues in the 1980s and 1990s. These include the deployment of SS-20 missiles by the Warsaw pact, the subsequent American deployment of Pershing missiles in Western Europe as a countermeasure, and the elaboration of the Strategic Defense Initiative ("Star Wars") by the Reagan administration.
The EIS organized conferences, produced publications, and served as a network of like-minded specialists in security issues. As the eventual vice-president of the EIS, Garnier-Lançon served as an intermediary between French conservative circles and their counterparts elsewhere in Europe, in the United Kingdom, and the United States.
Garnier-Lançon traveled extensively, both on behalf of the EIS and in her capacity as adjointe au maire (deputy) in the Paris mayor's office. The extensive CONFERENCES, SEMINARS, AND MEETINGS FILE and TRAVEL FILE record her participation in various gatherings, and contain numerous conference papers, speeches, and related materials. The CONFERENCES series also contains some documents pertaining to Garnier-Lançon's attendance at the closed deliberations of an exclusive group known only as Le Cercle (sometimes referred to as Le Cercle Pinay and, later, as Le Cercle Violet) whose activities have attracted the attention of analysts interested in elite groupings and their influence upon policy decisions made by Western governments.
The SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series of the papers contains Garnier-Lançon's own articles and public remarks, although a few additional items are interspersed elsewhere in the collection, where they are identified. Her role as a woman active in the higher circles of French conservative politics is documented in the CORRESPONDENCE series and the MOUVEMENT POUR LA SOCIÉTÉ DE DÉVELOPPEMENT FILE. The SOUND RECORDINGS series contains interviews with a number of leading French politicians, included Jacques Chirac, with whom Garnier-Lançon worked closely. Many of these interviews were conducted by Garnier-Lançon, who worked as a journalist before entering politics.
As much as possible, the organization of the papers reflects their original order and Garnier-Lançon's own descriptions and headings.
European Institute for Security.; PEN (Organization); Anti-communist movements.; Conservatism.; Europe--Defenses.; Europe.; France--Foreign relations--1945-; France--Relations.; France.; Journalists.; Paris (France); Security, International.
- Biographical File, 1973-1989 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, curricula vitae, employment application, membership card, press pass, programs, schedule, and transcript of speech, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings, 1973-1987 (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes materials in Arabic, English, German, Greek, and Italian
  - Curricula vitae, 1983-1989 (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes detailed summary of Garnier-Lançon's career and contacts in foreign countries
  - Employment application for NATO post, 1989 (Folder 1: 3)
    Includes correspondence with Jean-Michel Vidal
  - Membership card, National Press Club (Washington, D.C.), 1984 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Press pass, Reagan-Gorbachev summit, Washington, D.C., 1987 December (Folder 1: 5)
  - Programs, 1976-1987 (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes program for ceremony in which Garnier-Lançon was awarded the Croix de chevalier de la Léon d'honneur, Paris, 1976 October 7
  - Schedule detailing Garnier-Lançon's activities as vice-chairman of the European Institute for Security, 1985 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Transcript of speech by Maurice Robert introducing Garnier-Lançon at a meeting of Club 89, Paris, 1986 December 17 (Folder 1: 8)
- Correspondence, 1970-1995 (Box 1-7)
  Cards, enclosures, invitations, and letters, arranged alphabetically within two groups by name of correspondent or country and region
  - General
    - Christmas and New Year's cards, 1982-1991 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Invitations, 1970-1990 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Countries and regions (Box 2)
    - Asia, 1985-1986 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Denmark, 1980-1981 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Germany (West), 1982-1986 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Great Britain, 1982-1986 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Greece, 1981-1982 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Israel, 1983 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Italy, 1979-1986 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Latin America, 1983-1986 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Middle East, 1979-1986 (Folder 2: 9)
    - South Africa, 1983-1985 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Spain, 1984-1986 (Folder 2: 11)
    - United States, 1980-1989 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Individuals and organizations
    - Unidentified, 1982-1988 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Aghilipour, U., 1983 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Ahrweiler, Hélène, 1987 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Ajouz, Alya and Wafic, 1982-1983 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Allen, Richard, 1984-1986 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Amery, Julian, 1983 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Andreotti, Giulio, 1985-1991 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Aurillac, Michel, 1982-1984 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Bach, Franz Josef, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Balladur, Edouard, 1979 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Bark, Dennis L., 1984-1994 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Barre, Raymond, 1983-1985 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Beladiez, Emilio, 1984-1986 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Benavente Urbina, Andres, 1989-1990 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Benoist, Jean Marie, 1987 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Berg, Hans van den, 1988 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Bering-Jensen, Henrik, 1986-1987 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Bignier, Michel, 1988 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Billaud, Bernard, 1980-1983 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Bofill, Maria Elena, 1986-1987 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Bolufer, Jean-Paul, 1982 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Boyer, Daniel, 1982 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Bukovsky, Vladimir, 1986 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Burch, Geoffrey, 1983 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Bush, George H. W., 1981 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Cahen, Alfred, 1987-1988 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Calmels, Norbert, 1980-1984 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Canadian Conservative Center (William Campbell), 1985-1986 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Chaban-Delmas, Jacques, 1970-1985 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Chalfont, Lord, 1985-1987 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Chirac, Jacques, 1978-1989 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Cirino, Julio A., 1988-1989 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Close, Robert, 1982-1986 (Folder 3: 25)
    - Club de Paris: de la dissidence à la démocratie (Galia Ackerman), 1996 (Folder 3: 26)
    - Cluzel, Jean-Paul, 1971, 1996 (Folder 3: 27)
    - Conservatives Abroad, 1989 (Folder 3: 28)
    - Crozier, Brian, 1982-1993 (Folder 3: 29)
    - Cutter, Paul S., 1982-1984 (Folder 3: 30)
    - Debré, Michel, 1971-1973 (Folder 3: 31)
    - Delaunay, Jean, 1981-1982 (Folder 3: 32)
    - Derwinski, Edward J., 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Dib, Boutros, 1983 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Diesel, Anne, 1985 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Diop, Hamet, 1979 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Dominati, Jacques, 1987 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Dorminey, A. Blair, 1985-1986 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Dreier, David, 1985 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Edwards, Lee, 1983-1987 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Entwistle, Pamela, 1983-1984 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Fabian, Sharon L., 1986-1988 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Farah, Naoum, 1983 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Favorite, Joseph J., 1985 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Fergusson, Nigel, 1987 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Ferrada, Luis Valentin, 1986-1988 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Fieyra, Jacques, 1986-1988 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Fisher, John, 1984 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Fitzgerald, David, 1985 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Focart, Jacques, 1971, 1987 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Ford, Peter, 1985 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Fougier, Guy, 1985-1986 (Folder 4: 20)
    - Friedmann Mirochnik, Efrain, 1988 (Folder 4: 21)
    - Gabriel, Jean-Pierre, 1988 (Folder 4: 22)
    - Gallois, Pierre M., 1983 (Folder 4: 23)
    - Garnier, Roseline, 1989 (Folder 4: 24)
    - Gemayel, Pierre and Solange, 1983 (Folder 4: 25)
    - Gérard, Jean, 1984 (Folder 4: 26)
    - Gill, James H., 1984-1985 (Folder 4: 27)
    - Girard, André, 1980 (Folder 4: 28)
    - Giscard d'Estaing, Valéry, 1974-1988 (Folder 4: 29)
    - Giuliani, François, 1983-1986 (Folder 4: 30)
    - Goolsby, Charles, 1984 (Folder 4: 31)
    - Gomez Hurtado, Enrique, 1988 (Folder 4: 32)
    - Gorbachev, Mikhail, 1993-1995 (Folder 4: 33)
    - Gori, Umberto, 1987 (Folder 4: 34)
    - Graage, France K., 1987 (Folder 4: 35)
    - Graham, John, 1988 (Folder 4: 36)
    - Gregussen, John A., 1982 (Folder 4: 37)
    - Groux, Richard W., 1985 (Folder 4: 38)
    - Guirard, Jim, Jr., 1983-1987 (Folder 4: 39)
    - Guirguis, Sonia, 1979 (Folder 4: 40)
    - Guthman, Jack, 1983-1986 (Folder 4: 41)
    - Guzman Lyon, Roberto, 1988 (Folder 4: 42)
    - Habsbourg, Otto de, 1982-1989 (Folder 4: 43)
    - Hajdenberg, Henri, 1989 (Folder 4: 44)
    - Haley, June, 1983-1985 (Folder 4: 45)
    - Halot, Alexandre, 1982 (Folder 4: 46)
    - Hamilius, Jean-Pierre, 1988 (Folder 4: 47)
    - Hassel, Karl-Uwe von, 1985 (Folder 4: 48)
    - Hauser, Wulf G., 1988 (Folder 4: 49)
    - Healey, Denis, 1986 (Folder 4: 50)
    - Herbst, Axel, 1985-1986 (Folder 4: 51)
    - Hernu, Charles, 1984 (Folder 4: 52)
    - High Frontier (Robert C. Richardson III), 1984 (Folder 4: 53)
    - Hinrichs, Merle A., 1983 (Folder 4: 54)
    - Hoffman, Donald A., 1984 (Folder 4: 55)
    - Hossein, Robert, 1988 (Folder 4: 56)
    - Houtom, Robert von, 1988 (Folder 4: 57)
    - Ikle, Fred, 1985-1986 (Folder 4: 58)
    - Institut français des relations internationales (Dominique Moïsi, Thierry de Montbrial), 1982-1988 (Folder 4: 59)
    - Institute for the Study of Terrorism (Jillian Becker, Lucie Okoniewski), 1986-1987 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - International Freedom Foundation (Marc Gordon), 1988 (Folder 5: 2)
    - International Policy Forum (Morton Blackwell, Françoise Mizrahi), 1984-1989 (Folder 5: 3)
    - International Security Council (Jean-Pierre Gabriel), 1988 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Johnstone, Homer, 1984-1985 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Jolis, Albert, 1985-1989 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Jonet, Jacques G., 1982-1987 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Joxe, Pierre, 1992 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Juppé, Alain, 1988 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Kamal, Hassan, 1987 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Kampelman, Max M., 1985 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Kirkpatrick, Jeane R., 1982-1984 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Knoche, H. G., 1985-1986 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Koch, Georges, 1983 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Kohl, Helmut, 1982-1994 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Kotas, Jiří, 1985 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Kraemer, Sven, 1985 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Kunz, Gerhard, 1982-1983 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Labbez, Louis, 1985 (Folder 5: 19)
    - Lanversin, Bernard de, undated (Folder 5: 20)
    - Lasky, Melvin J., 1985 (Folder 5: 21)
    - Lattès, Robert, 1982 (Folder 5: 22)
    - Le Chêne, Evelyn, 1984 (Folder 5: 23)
    - Leante, Lucio, 1988 (Folder 5: 24)
    - Lefever, Ernest W., 1984-1987 (Folder 5: 25)
    - Leigh, Edward, undated (Folder 5: 26)
    - Lenczowski, John, 1990 (Folder 5: 27)
    - Lenz, Carl, 1984 (Folder 5: 28)
    - Leshem, Moshe, 1987 (Folder 5: 29)
    - Lévêque, Jean-Maxime, 1983 (Folder 5: 30)
    - Lietaer, B., 1982 (Folder 5: 31)
    - Luns, J. M. A. H., 1985 (Folder 5: 32)
    - Lustiger, Cardinal, 1987 (Folder 5: 33)
    - Maitland, Olga, 1983-1988 (Folder 5: 34)
    - Mauroy, Pierre, 1980 (Folder 5: 35)
    - McCausland, Jeff, 1982-1984 (Folder 5: 36)
    - McFarlane, Robert, 1985 (Folder 5: 37)
    - Meo, Jean, 1982 (Folder 5: 38)
    - Messmer, Pierre, 1973 (Folder 5: 39)
    - Michelet, Edmond, 1969-1970 (Folder 5: 40)
    - Mitterrand, François, 1989-1993 (Folder 5: 41)
    - Montand, Yves, 1984-1987 (Folder 5: 42)
    - Munroe, Mary and Patrick, 1984-1987 (Folder 5: 43)
    - Muth, Albrecht G., 1983 (Folder 5: 44)
    - Naftalski, Daniel, 1986 (Folder 5: 45)
    - Narbone, Luigi, 1987-1988 (Folder 5: 46)
    - Narjes, Karl-Heinz, 1983 (Folder 5: 47)
    - NAVO-Kring (Jan Plas, Herman Willemse), 1988-1989 (Folder 5: 48)
    - Nelson, Ronald, 1985-1988 (Folder 5: 49)
    - Olvey, Lee D., 1982 (Folder 5: 50)
    - Pandraud, Robert, 1983 (Folder 5: 51)
    - Parrott, G. N. "Polly,", 1985 (Folder 5: 52)
    - Pen Club (Gabi Gleichmann, Claude Harel, György Konrad, Boris Novack, Jean Robert), 1991-1993 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Peyrefitte, Alain, 1972 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Pflimlin, Pierre, 1984-1988 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Phillips, Howard, 1986-1994 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Pipes, Richard, 1983 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Pirchner, Herman, Jr., 1990-1991 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Platt, Stuart, 1985 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Poher, Alain, 1986 (Folder 6: 8)
    - Prevot, Michel F., 1985-1988 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Quentin, Didier, 1986-1989 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Rababy, Sami, 1981-1987 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Ramaer, J. C., 1982-1986 (Folder 6: 12)
    - Reagan, Ronald and Nancy, 1984-1985 (Folder 6: 13)
    - Rees, John, 1984-1987 (Folder 6: 14)
    - Regan, D. E., 1986 (Folder 6: 15)
    - Reineke, Wolfgang, 1985-1986 (Folder 6: 16)
    - Reinhardt, Klaus, 1986 (Folder 6: 17)
    - Renard, Pierre-Henri, 1982-1987 (Folder 6: 18)
    - Reno, Barbara Morrison, 1985 (Folder 6: 19)
    - Resistance International (Edouard Kuznetsov, Vladimir Maximov, Alexandra Schmidt, Olga Svintsvova), 1982-1987 (Folder 6: 20)
    - Revel, Jean-François, 1985 (Folder 6: 21)
    - Ripa di Meana, Carlo, 1985-1988 (Folder 6: 22)
    - Roach, Alfred, 1985-1986 (Folder 6: 23)
    - Romani, Roger, 1981-1985 (Folder 6: 24)
    - Romanones, Aline de, 1982-1983 (Folder 6: 25)
    - Rostolan, Michel de, 1984 (Folder 6: 26)
    - Rotary-Club de Saint-Avold, 1988 (Folder 6: 27)
    - Russy, Candace U. de, 1985 (Folder 6: 28)
    - Ryder, Hal, 1988-1989 (Folder 6: 29)
    - Salaam, Sa'eb, 1980-1983 (Folder 6: 30)
    - Sanchez Bella, Alfredo, 1983-1987 (Folder 6: 31)
    - Schäfer, Barbara, 1989 (Folder 6: 32)
    - Schoeller, Franz Joachen, 1985 (Folder 6: 33)
    - Schwank, Lucy, 1985 (Folder 6: 34)
    - Scruton, Roger, 1986 (Folder 6: 35)
    - Sernissi, Albert, 1978-1980 (Folder 6: 36)
    - Shakher, Burhan, 1984 (Folder 6: 37)
    - Shakley, Ted, 1983 (Folder 6: 38)
    - Shea, Jamie, 1983-1991 (Folder 6: 39)
    - Sher, Yoël, 1984 (Folder 6: 40)
    - Souchon, Anne-Catherine, 1988 (Folder 6: 41)
    - Spadolini, Giovanni, 1985 (Folder 6: 42)
    - Spaeth, Lothar, 1982-1989 (Folder 6: 43)
    - Special Forces Club, 1988 (Folder 6: 44)
    - Staar, Richard, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Taulelle, Jean, 1976 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Tavernier, René, 1986-1988 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Thatcher, Margaret, 1985 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Theberge, James D., 1987 (Folder 7: 5)
    - Thomas, Hugh, 1986-1988 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Tobar, Hernan, 1983 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Tomasini, René, 1971-1982 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Tyson, Patti Birge, 1982-1984 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Union européenne féminine (Jacqueline Magnan de Bornier, Marise Goldsmith-Dansaert), 1985-1987 (Folder 7: 10)
    - Vandervoorde, Pierre, 1985-1988 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Védrine, Hubert, 1988-1989 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Veil, Simone, undated (Folder 7: 13)
    - Wajsman, Patrick, 1988 (Folder 7: 14)
    - Wall, Patrick, 1983 (Folder 7: 15)
    - Weinberger, Caspar, 1986 (Folder 7: 16)
    - Weizsäcker, Richard von, 1984 (Folder 7: 17)
    - West European Defence Association (Evelyn Le Chêne), 1985-1987 (Folder 7: 18)
    - Weyrich, Paul, undated (Folder 7: 19)
    - Whitney, Ray, 1987 (Folder 7: 20)
    - Wolff, Elmer, 1985-1986 (Folder 7: 21)
    - Yaacovy, Yitzchak, 1983 (Folder 7: 22)
    - Yankelevitch, Ephram and Tatiana, 1985 (Folder 7: 23)
    - Zagladine, Vadim, 1993-1995 (Folder 7: 24)
- Speeches and Writings, 1971-1993 (Box 7-9)
  Articles, conference papers, correspondence, and transcripts of speeches, arranged chronologically
  - "Une agence pour une meilleure information,", undated (Folder 7: 25)
    Holograph notes and typescript
  - "'Atlantisme' et réalisme,", undated (Folder 7: 26)
    Typescript
  - "Attention...danger!", undated (Folder 7: 27)
  - "Les coulisses du sommet,", undated (Folder 7: 28)
  - "Est-ce la mort du cèdre?", undated (Folder 7: 29)
  - "Note sur la position européenne vis-à-vis S.D.I.,", undated (Folder 7: 30)
  - "La politique agricole commune,", undated (Folder 7: 31)
  - "Pro-Freedom Activism in Europe,", undated (Folder 7: 32)
    Holograph draft
  - "Quelques notes brèves sur différents organismes internationaux,", undated (Folder 7: 33)
  - Speech on West European defense issues, undated (Folder 7: 34)
  - "Aux sources d'un conflit," La Nation, 1971 January 7 (Folder 7: 35)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Notes de voyage,", 1973 (Folder 7: 36)
    Holograph notes
  - "La communauté européenne: chronologie et étapes, 1950-1982," (Folder 7: 37)
  - "The Price of Liberty,", 1982 (Folder 7: 38)
  - "L'Europe et l'avenir du monde libre," Rassemblement pour la république meeting, Paris, France, 1982 January 23-24 (Folder 7: 39)
  - Speech on Christianity and peace, 1982 March 22 (Folder 7: 40)
  - Speech on the defense of Western Europe, 1982 April 15 (Folder 7: 41)
  - Speech, congress of the Women's Union of the Christian Democratic Union, Freiburg im Briesgau, West Germany, 1982 September 11 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Correspondence, program, and typescript. In French, with German translation
  - Address to the Woman's National Democratic Club, Washington, D.C., 1982 November (?) (Folder 8: 2)
    Correspondence and typescript
  - "Le prix de la liberté,", 1983 (Folder 8: 3)
    Holograph and typescript
  - Closing speech, 28th Congress, Fédération des associations franco-allemandes, Paris, 1983 October 2 (Folder 8: 4)
  - "Being Realistic about the Atlantic Alliance,", 1984 (Folder 8: 5)
  - "Ce qu'il faut savoir aussi sur le Nicaragua,", 1984 (Folder 8: 6)
    Notes, holograph draft, and typescript
  - L'Europe en libertés, co-author, 1984 (Folder 8: 7)
    Printed copy
  - Speech on the Middle East situation, 1984 January (Folder 8: 8)
  - Speech on European defense policy, National Press Club, Washington, D.C., 1984 October 24 (Folder 8: 9)
  - "La guerre des étoiles," interview, Aviation 2000, 1984 December (Folder 8: 10)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy
  - "De la désinformation," speech, Conference sur le rôle de la désinformation dans le monde moderne, 1984 December (Folder 8: 11)
  - Speech on Baltic independence, Helsinki, Finland, 1985 July 28 (Folder 8: 12)
  - "Eureka and S.D.I.,", 1985 September 21 (Folder 8: 13)
    Program and typescript
  - "U.S.A./U.R.S.S., la diplomatie des différences ou les différences de la diplomatie,", 1985 October 3 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Speech, The Red Orchestra: Instruments of Soviet Foreign Policy in Africa, conference sponsored by the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford University, Washington, D.C., 1986 July 1-2 (Folder 8: 15)
  - "Mériter la confiance,", 1987 January 8 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Speech, meeting of l'Union européenne féminine, 1987 February 12 (Folder 8: 17)
    Holograph, typescript, and press clippings
  - "European Defence-A Global Approach," Swinton Memorial Lecture, Conservative Political Centre summer school, Oxford, 1987 July 11 (Folder 8: 18)
    Correspondence, program, holograph, and typescript
  - "Cuba et la sécurité régionale," conference paper, Cuba bajo análisis: realidad y perspectives," Buenos Aires, 1988 June 28 (Folder 8: 19)
  - "Position de la France en matière de désarmement," conference paper, II Congreso internacional de estudios sovieticos, Buenos Aires, 1988 October 2-5 (Folder 8: 20)
  - Speech, Internationaler Frauentag, conference, Stuttgart, 1989 March 8 (Folder 8: 21)
    Correspondence, holograph, and typescript
  - "La situation économique en URSS," speech, Navro-King conference, Louvain, Belgium, 1989 October 10 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - "Une réponse franco-allemande aux défís de demain," Actuel, no. 12, 1991 (Folder 9: 2)
  - "The Armed Forces and Military Service in a Democratic State," speech, Moscow, 1991 November 25 (Folder 9: 3)
  - "A propos de Maastricht: une réflexion raisonnable et documentée," La Lettre, no. 11., 1992 September (Folder 9: 4)
  - "L'honneur, le bon sens, l'intérêt supérieur de la patrie,", 1992 September 3 (Folder 9: 5)
  - "Some Remarks on a Greater Europe,", 1993 (Folder 9: 6)
  - "Lieu et destin," speech, 59th international congress, PEN Club, Dubrovnik, Croatia, 1993 April 24 (Folder 9: 7)
  - "Suis-je le gardien de mon frère?" speech, 26th international meeting of writers, Bled, Slovenia, 1993 May 25-29 (Folder 9: 8)
- European Institute for Security Matters (EIS) File, 1982-1995 (Box 9-21)
  Correspondence, dossiers, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1982-1983 (Folder 9: 9)
      - 1984 (Folder 9: 10)
      - 1985 (Folder 9: 11)
      - 1986 (Folder 9: 12)
      - 1987 (Folder 9: 13)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - 1989 (Folder 10: 2)
      - 1990 (Folder 10: 3)
      - 1991 (Folder 10: 4)
      - 1992-1993 (Folder 10: 5)
      - 1994 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Anderson, Ellen, 1988 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Andreani, Jacques, 1988 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Association de journalistes de la défense, 1987 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Augier, Philippe, 1989 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Baars, D. J., 1988 (Folder 10: 11)
    - Beer, John, 1988 (Folder 10: 12)
    - Bianco, Jean-Louis, 1986-1988 (Folder 10: 13)
    - Bloch, Alain, 1987 (Folder 10: 14)
    - Boulic, Jean-Yves, 1984-1985 (Folder 10: 15)
    - Burch, Geoffrey, 1987-1988 (Folder 10: 16)
    - Carrington, Lord, 1987-1988 (Folder 10: 17)
    - Chevènement, Jean-Pierre, 1988 (Folder 10: 18)
    - Close, Robert, 1985-1988 (Folder 10: 19)
    - Copel, Etienne, 1984-1985 (Folder 10: 20)
    - Corterier, Peter, 1988 (Folder 10: 21)
    - Cousté, P. B., 1987-1988 (Folder 10: 22)
    - Dake, A. C. A., 1988 (Folder 10: 23)
    - Dejaiffre, René, 1987 (Folder 10: 24)
    - Delatte, Jean-Louis, 1987 (Folder 10: 25)
    - Delaunay, Jean, 1984-1985 (Folder 10: 26)